Hi.
مرحباً.
I want to talk about understanding, and the nature of understanding,
أود التحدث إليكم عن عملية الفهم وطبيعة الفهم،
and what the essence of understanding is,
وعن ماهية جوهر الفهم،
because understanding is something we aim for, everyone.
لأن الفهم أمر نهدف إليه، جميعنا.
We want to understand things.
إذ أننا نود فهم الأمور.
My claim is that understanding has to do
ادعائي هو أنَّ الفهم أمر له علاقة
with the ability to change your perspective.
بقدرتنا على تغيير منظورنا.
If you don't have that, you don't have understanding.
إن كنتم لا تمتلكونها، فليست لديكم الكمية الكافية من الفهم.
So that is my claim.
لذا فهذا ادعائي.
And I want to focus on mathematics.
وأريد أن أركز على الرياضيات،
Many of us think of mathematics as addition, subtraction,
العديد منا يعتقد أن الرياضيات هي عبارة عن الجمع والطرح
multiplication, division,
والضرب والقسمة
fractions, percent, geometry, algebra -- all that stuff.
الكسور والنسب المئوية والمفاهيم الجيومترية وعلم الجبر ... كل هذه الأشياء.
But actually, I want to talk about the essence of mathematics as well.
ولكن في الحقيقة، أريد أن أتكلم عن جوهر الرياضيات
And my claim is that mathematics has to do with patterns.
وطرحي هنا هو أن الرياضيات مرتبطة بالأنماط.
Behind me, you see a beautiful pattern,
خلفي، ترون نمطًا رائعًا،
and this pattern actually emerges just from drawing circles
وهذا النمط ينتج عن رسم الدوائر وحسب
in a very particular way.
بطريقة محددة.
So my day-to-day definition of mathematics that I use every day
لذا تعريفي للرياضيات اليومية التي أستخدمها
is the following:
هو التالي:
First of all, it's about finding patterns.
بدايةً، إنها حول إيجاد الأنماط.
And by "pattern," I mean a connection, a structure, some regularity,
وأعني ب"الأنماط" اتصالات، وهيكلًا وبعض التناسق،
some rules that govern what we see.
بعض القواعد التي تضمن تشكيل ما نراه.
Second of all,
ثانياً،
I think it is about representing these patterns with a language.
أعتقد أنها حول تمثيل هذه الأنماط بواسطة لغة.
We make up language if we don't have it,
سنصنع لغةً إن لم نمتلكها،
and in mathematics, this is essential.
وفي الرياضيات، هذا أمر أساسي.
It's also about making assumptions
إنها أيضاً حول صنع الافتراضات
and playing around with these assumptions and just seeing what happens.
واللعب بهذه الافتراضات لنرى ماذا يحدث.
We're going to do that very soon.
سنقوم بفعل ذلك قريباً جداً.
And finally, it's about doing cool stuff.
وفي النهاية، إنها حول القيام بأعمال رائعة.
Mathematics enables us to do so many things.
الرياضيات تمكِّننا من القيام بالكثير من الأشياء.
So let's have a look at these patterns.
لذا دعونا نلقي نظرة على هذه الأنماط.
If you want to tie a tie knot,
إذا أردت أن تعقد ربطة العنق،
there are patterns.
فهناك أنماط.
Tie knots have names.
عقدات ربطة العنق لديها أسماء.
And you can also do the mathematics of tie knots.
ويمكن أيضاً أن تستخدم الرياضيات لعقد ربطة العنق.
This is a left-out, right-in, center-out and tie.
هذا هو الشمال خارجاً، اليمين داخلاً، المركز خارجاً واربط
This is a left-in, right-out, left-in, center-out and tie.
هذا هو الشمال داخلاً، اليمين خارجاً، اليسار خارجاً، المركز خارجاً واربط.
This is a language we made up for the patterns of tie knots,
هذه هي اللغة التي ابتكرناها لأنماط عقد ربطة العنق،
and a half-Windsor is all that.
وهذه هي عقدة نصف وندسور.
This is a mathematics book about tying shoelaces
هذا كتاب رياضيات حول عقد رباط الحذاء
at the university level,
في المستوى الجامعي،
because there are patterns in shoelaces.
لأن هناك العديد من الأنماط في رباط الحذاء.
You can do it in so many different ways.
يمكن أن تقوم بها بالعديد من الطرق.
We can analyze it.
يمكننا تحليلها.
We can make up languages for it.
يمكننا أن نختلق لغة خاصة لها.
And representations are all over mathematics.
وتمثيلها يتم بالكامل بواسطة الرياضيات.
This is Leibniz's notation from 1675.
هذا هو رمز لايبنتز من عام 1675.
He invented a language for patterns in nature.
لقد اخترع لغة للأنماط في الطبيعة.
When we throw something up in the air,
عندما نرمي شيئًا في الهواء،
it falls down.
سيسقط نحو الأرض.
Why?
لماذا؟
We're not sure, but we can represent this with mathematics in a pattern.
نحن لسنا متأكدين، لكن يمكننا أن نمثل ذلك بواسطة الرياضيات في نمط.
This is also a pattern.
وهذا أيضاً نمط.
This is also an invented language.
وهذه أيضاً لغة مخترَعة.
Can you guess for what?
هل يمكن أن تحزروا لماذا؟
It is actually a notation system for dancing, for tap dancing.
إنها في الحقيقة نظام رموز للرقص، للرقص النقري.
That enables him as a choreographer to do cool stuff, to do new things,
وهذا ما يمكِّن مصمم الرقص من عمل أشياء رائعة، من عمل أشياء جديدة،
because he has represented it.
لأنه قام بتمثيلها.
I want you to think about how amazing representing something actually is.
أريد أن تفكروا حول روعة تمثيل شيء ما.
Here it says the word "mathematics."
هنا تأتي الكلمة "رياضيات".
But actually, they're just dots, right?
ولكن في الحقيقة، إنها نقط وحسب، صحيح؟
So how in the world can these dots represent the word?
لذا كيف يمكن لهذه النقط أن تمثل الكلمة؟
Well, they do.
حسناً، إنها تمثلها.
They represent the word "mathematics,"
إنها تمثل الكلمة "رياضيات"،
and these symbols also represent that word
وهذه الرموز تمثل هذه الكلمة
and this we can listen to.
وهذا ما يمكننا سماعه.
It sounds like this.
إنها تبدو هكذا.
(Beeps)
(بيب)
Somehow these sounds represent the word and the concept.
بشكل ما، يمكن لهذا الصوت أن يمثل الكلمة والمبدأ.
How does this happen?
كيف يتم ذلك؟
There's something amazing going on about representing stuff.
هناك شيء رائع حول تمثيل الأشياء.
So I want to talk about that magic that happens
لذا أود التحدث عن السحر الذي يحدث
when we actually represent something.
عندما نمثل شيئاً.
Here you see just lines with different widths.
هنا نرى مجرد خطوط مختلفة في العرض.
They stand for numbers for a particular book.
إنها تحل محل الأعداد في كتاب محدد.
And I can actually recommend this book, it's a very nice book.
ويمكنني أن أنصحكم بهذا الكتاب، إنه كتاب رائع جداً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Just trust me.
فقط ثقوا بي.
OK, so let's just do an experiment,
حسناً، لذا دعونا نقوم بتجربة،
just to play around with some straight lines.
فقط لنعبث ببعض الخطوط المستقيمة،
This is a straight line.
هذا خط مستقيم.
Let's make another one.
دعونا ننشئ واحدًا آخر.
So every time we move, we move one down and one across,
لذا فكل مرة نتحرك فيها، نتحرك مرة للأسفل ومرة للجانب،
and we draw a new straight line, right?
ونرسم خطاً مستقيماً جديداً، صحيح؟
We do this over and over and over,
نقوم بهذا مراراً وتكراراً،
and we look for patterns.
ونبحث عن الأنماط.
So this pattern emerges,
لذا هذا النمط ينتج،
and it's a rather nice pattern.
وهذا نمط رائع.
It looks like a curve, right?
إنه يبدو مثل منحنى، صحيح؟
Just from drawing simple, straight lines.
فقط عبر رسم خطوط مستقيمة وبسيطة.
Now I can change my perspective a little bit. I can rotate it.
الآن أستطيع أن أغير منظوري قليلاً. أستطيع أن أديرها.
Have a look at the curve.
ألقوا نظرة على المنحنى.
What does it look like?
كيف يبدو؟
Is it a part of a circle?
هل هو جزء من دائرة؟
It's actually not a part of a circle.
إنه في الحقيقة ليس جزءًا من دائرة.
So I have to continue my investigation and look for the true pattern.
لذا يجب أن أكمل تحقيقي وأبحث عن حقيقة النمط.
Perhaps if I copy it and make some art?
ربما إذا نسخته وصنعت لوحة فنية؟
Well, no.
حسناً، لا.
Perhaps I should extend the lines like this,
ربما يجب أن أُمدِّد الخطوط هكذا،
and look for the pattern there.
وأبحث عن النمط هناك.
Let's make more lines.
دعونا ننشئ المزيد من الخطوط.
We do this.
قمنا بهذا.
And then let's zoom out and change our perspective again.
ونصغِّر الصورة حتى نغير منظورنا مجدداً.
Then we can actually see that what started out as just straight lines
ومن ثم يمكننا أن نرى أن ما بدأناه كخطوط مستقيمة وحسب
is actually a curve called a parabola.
هو في الحقيقة شكل منحنى يدعى القطع المكافئ.
This is represented by a simple equation,
والذي يمكن أن يتم تمثيله بواسطة معادلة بسيطة،
and it's a beautiful pattern.
وهو نمط رائع.
So this is the stuff that we do.
لذا فهذه الأشياء التي نقوم بها.
We find patterns, and we represent them.
نجد الأنماط ونقوم بتمثيلها.
And I think this is a nice day-to-day definition.
وأعتقد أن هذا تعريف يومي رائع.
But today I want to go a little bit deeper,
لكن اليوم أود أن أذهب أعمق قليلاً،
and think about what the nature of this is.
وأفكر في طبيعة هذا.
What makes it possible?
ما الذي يجعله ممكنًا؟
There's one thing that's a little bit deeper,
هناك شيء واحد أعمق بقليل،
and that has to do with the ability to change your perspective.
والذي يتعلق بالقدرة على تغيير منظوركم.
And I claim that when you change your perspective,
وأفترض أنك عندما تغير منظورك،
and if you take another point of view,
وإذا أخذنا وجهة نظر أخرى،
you learn something new about what you are watching
فستتعلم شيئاً جديداً حول ما تشاهده
or looking at or hearing.
أو تنظر إليه أو تسمعه.
And I think this is a really important thing that we do all the time.
وأعتقد أن هذا أمر في غاية الأهمية وأمر نقوم به طوال الوقت.
So let's just look at this simple equation,
لذا دعونا ننظر إلى هذه المعادلة البسيطة،
x + x = 2 • x.
x+x=2*x
This is a very nice pattern, and it's true,
إنه نمط رائع للغاية وهذا صحيح،
because 5 + 5 = 2 • 5, etc.
لأن 5+5=2*5 ، وهكذا.
We've seen this over and over, and we represent it like this.
نرى ذلك مراراً تكراراً ونمثل ذلك كالآتي.
But think about it: this is an equation.
ولكن فكروا في ذلك: هذه معادلة.
It says that something is equal to something else,
إنها تقول أن شيئًا مساوٍ لشيء آخر،
and that's two different perspectives.
وهذا يمثل منظورين مختلفين.
One perspective is, it's a sum.
أحد المنظورين هو، أنها عملية جمع.
It's something you plus together.
إنها جمع شيئين مع بعضهما.
On the other hand, it's a multiplication,
من ناحية أخرى، إنها عملية ضرب،
and those are two different perspectives.
وهذان منظوران مختلفان.
And I would go as far as to say that every equation is like this,
وأريد أن أذهب أبعد وأقول أن كل معادلة هي بهذا الشكل،
every mathematical equation where you use that equality sign
كل معادلة رياضية تستخدم إشارة المساواة
is actually a metaphor.
ما هي إلا استعارة مجازية.
It's an analogy between two things.
ما هو إلا مماثلة لطرفين.
You're just viewing something and taking two different points of view,
أنت تعرض شيئاً من وجهتي نظر مختلفتين.
and you're expressing that in a language.
وتعبر عن ذلك باللغة.
Have a look at this equation.
ألقوا نظرة على هذه المعادلة.
This is one of the most beautiful equations.
إنها واحدة من أجمل المعادلات.
It simply says that, well,
إنها تقول ببساطة، حسناً،
two things, they're both -1.
أن شيئين، يساوي كلاهما 1-.
This thing on the left-hand side is -1, and the other one is.
هذا الشيء على الجانب الأيسر يساوي 1- ونفس الشيء على الجانب الآخر.
And that, I think, is one of the essential parts
وهذا، كما أعتقد واحد من الأجزاء الرئيسية
of mathematics -- you take different points of view.
للرياضيات... إنك تأخذ وجهات نظر مختلفة.
So let's just play around.
لذا دعونا نلعب معاً.
Let's take a number.
دعونا نأخذ عدداً.
We know four-thirds. We know what four-thirds is.
نحن نعلم ما هي أربعة أثلاث. نحن نعلم ما تمثله.
It's 1.333, but we have to have those three dots,
إنها 1.333 ولكننا يجب أن نحصل على هذه النقاط الثلاث،
otherwise it's not exactly four-thirds.
وإلا لن تكون أربعة أثلاث كاملة.
But this is only in base 10.
ولكن هذا فقط في الأساس 10.
You know, the number system, we use 10 digits.
أنتم تعلمون، نظام العد، نحن نستخدم النظام العشري.
If we change that around and only use two digits,
إن غيرنا ذلك واستخدمنا رقمين فقط،
that's called the binary system.
فإن ذلك يدعى بالنظام الثنائي.
It's written like this.
وهو يكتب هكذا.
So we're now talking about the number.
لذا نحن الآن نتحدث عن العدد.
The number is four-thirds.
والعدد هو أربعة أثلاث.
We can write it like this,
يمكن كتابته هكذا،
and we can change the base, change the number of digits,
ويمكننا بتغيير الأساس، تغيير عدد الأرقام
and we can write it differently.
ويمكننا كتابته بشكل مختلف.
So these are all representations of the same number.
لذا هذه كلها تمثيلات للعدد نفسه.
We can even write it simply, like 1.3 or 1.6.
ويمكن حتى أن نكتبه بشكل أبسط مثل 1.3 أو 1.6.
It all depends on how many digits you have.
هذا يعتمد على عدد الأرقام لديك.
Or perhaps we just simplify and write it like this.
أو ربما يمكننا تبسيطه وكتابته على هذه الصورة.
I like this one, because this says four divided by three.
أحب هذه بالتحديد، لأنها تقول أربعة مقسومة على ثلاثة.
And this number expresses a relation between two numbers.
وهذا العدد يمثل علاقة بين عددين.
You have four on the one hand and three on the other.
لدينا أربعة على هذا الجانب وثلاثة على الجانب الآخر.
And you can visualize this in many ways.
ويمكننا تصور ذلك بالعديد من الطرق.
What I'm doing now is viewing that number from different perspectives.
ما أفعله الآن هو أني أستعرض لكم ذلك الرقم من وجهات مختلفة.
I'm playing around.
إني أعبث وحسب.
I'm playing around with how we view something,
ألعب بكيفية عرض شيء معين.
and I'm doing it very deliberately.
وأنا أفعل ذلك عن عمد.
We can take a grid.
يمكننا أخذ شبكة.
If it's four across and three up, this line equals five, always.
إذا كانت أربعة مربعات جانبية وثلاثة علوية، فهذا الخط يساوي خمسة دائماً.
It has to be like this. This is a beautiful pattern.
يجب أن تبدو هكذا. إنه نمط جميل.
Four and three and five.
أربعة وثلاثة وخمسة.
And this rectangle, which is 4 x 3,
وهذا المستطيل، الذي مساحته 4x3
you've seen a lot of times.
أنتم ترونه في كثير من الوقت.
This is your average computer screen.
إنه معدل مساحة شاشة حاسوبكم.
800 x 600 or 1,600 x 1,200
800x600 أو 1600x1200
is a television or a computer screen.
إنها شاشة تلفاز أو شاشة حاسوب.
So these are all nice representations,
لذا هذه كلها تمثيلات رائعة،
but I want to go a little bit further and just play more with this number.
ولكن أرغب أن أذهب أبعد قليلاً وألعب أكثر بهذا العدد.
Here you see two circles. I'm going to rotate them like this.
هنا نرى دائرتين، أريد أن أديرهما هكذا.
Observe the upper-left one.
راقب تلك التي في أعلى اليسار.
It goes a little bit faster, right?
إنها تتحرك بشكل أسرع قليلاً، أليس كذلك؟
You can see this.
يمكنكم رؤية ذلك.
It actually goes exactly four-thirds as fast.
إنها فعلياً تتحرك أسرع بأربعة أثلاث.
That means that when it goes around four times,
وهذا يعني أنها عندما تدور أربع مرات،
the other one goes around three times.
فإن الأخرى تدور ثلاث مرات.
Now let's make two lines, and draw this dot where the lines meet.
الآن دعونا ننشئ خطين ونرسم هذه النقطة عند التقاء الخطين.
We get this dot dancing around.
سنحصل على هذه النقطة ترقص حولها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And this dot comes from that number.
وهذه النقطة ناتجة عن هذا العدد.
Right? Now we should trace it.
صحيح؟ الآن يجب علينا أن نرسمها.
Let's trace it and see what happens.
دعونا نرسمها ونرى ماذا يحدث.
This is what mathematics is all about.
هذا ما تدور حوله الرياضيات.
It's about seeing what happens.
إنها تدور حول رؤية ما سيحدث.
And this emerges from four-thirds.
وهذا ما نتج عن الأربعة أثلاث.
I like to say that this is the image of four-thirds.
أحب أن أقول أن هذه هي صورة الأربعة أثلاث.
It's much nicer -- (Cheers)
إنها أجمل بكثير... (هتاف)
Thank you!
شكراً لكم!
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
This is not new.
إنه أمر ليس بجديد.
This has been known for a long time, but --
إنه معروف منذ وقت طويل، لكن...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But this is four-thirds.
ولكن هذه هي الأربعة أثلاث.
Let's do another experiment.
دعونا نقوم تجربة أخرى.
Let's now take a sound, this sound: (Beep)
دعونا نأخذ الآن صوتاً، هذا الصوت: (بيب)
This is a perfect A, 440Hz.
هذا هو حرف (أ) مثالي، 440 هيرتز.
Let's multiply it by two.
دعونا نضربه باثنين.
We get this sound. (Beep)
نحصل على هذا الصوت. (بيب)
When we play them together, it sounds like this.
عند تشغيلهم معاً، يبدو الصوت هكذا.
We can do this game. We can play a sound, play the same A.
يمكننا لعب هذه اللعبة. يمكننا تشغيل صوت، شغل نفس صوت (أ).
We can multiply it by three-halves.
يمكننا ضربه بثلاثة أنصاف.
(Beep)
(بيب)
This is what we call a perfect fifth.
هذا ما ندعوه بالخمس المثالي.
They sound really nice together.
إن صوتها جميل معاً.
Let's multiply this sound by four-thirds. (Beep)
دعونا نضرب هذا الصوت بأربعة أثلاث. (بيب)
What happens?
ماذا حدث؟
You get this sound. (Beep)
لقد حصلنا على هذا الصوت (بيب)
This is the perfect fourth.
إنه ربع مثالي.
If the first one is an A, this is a D.
إن كان الصوت الأول (أ) فإن هذا الصوت هو (ث).
They sound like this together. (Beeps)
يبدو صوتها معاً هكذا (بيب)
This is the sound of four-thirds.
إنه صوت الأربعة أثلاث.
What I'm doing now, I'm changing my perspective.
ما أفعله الآن هو أنني أغير منظوري.
I'm just viewing a number from another perspective.
إني أعرض العدد من منظور آخر.
I can even do this with rhythms, right?
يمكنني حتى فعل ذلك باستخدام إيقاع، صحيح؟
I can take a rhythm and play three beats at one time (Drumbeats)
يمكنني أخذ صوت إيقاعي وعزف ثلاث ضربات مرة واحدة (أصوات قرع الطبول)
in a period of time,
في مدة زمنية محددة،
and I can play another sound four times in that same space.
ويمكنني عزف صوت آخر أربع مرات في نفس المجال.
(Clanking sounds)
(أصوات قعقعة)
Sounds kind of boring, but listen to them together.
تبدو أصواتًا مملة ولكن استمع إليها معاً.
(Drumbeats and clanking sounds)
(أصوات قرع الطبول وأصوات قعقعة)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Hey! So.
ها! لذا.
I can even make a little hi-hat.
ويمكنني حتى أن أجعلها أجمل قليلاً.
(Drumbeats and cymbals)
(أصوات قرع الطبول وقرع الصنج)
Can you hear this?
هل باستطاعتكم سماع هذا؟
So, this is the sound of four-thirds.
لذا، هذا هو صوت الأربعة أثلاث.
Again, this is as a rhythm.
مجدداً، فهو هكذا كصوت إيقاعي.
(Drumbeats and cowbell)
(أصوات قرع الطبول وقرع الجرس)
And I can keep doing this and play games with this number.
وأستطيع أن أستمر بفعل ذلك وألعب بهذا العدد.
Four-thirds is a really great number. I love four-thirds!
إن العدد أربعة أثلاث هو عدد عظيم. أنا أحب عدد الأربعة أثلاث!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Truly -- it's an undervalued number.
بصدق... إنه عدد مستخَف به.
So if you take a sphere and look at the volume of the sphere,
لذا إذا نظرتم إلى كرة ونظرتم إلى حجم الكرة،
it's actually four-thirds of some particular cylinder.
إنه فعلياً يساوي أربعة أثلاث حجم أسطوانة معينة.
So four-thirds is in the sphere. It's the volume of the sphere.
لذا فإن الأربعة أثلاث موجود في الكرة. إنه حجم الكرة.
OK, so why am I doing all this?
حسناً، لذا لم أقوم بكل هذا؟
Well, I want to talk about what it means to understand something
حسناً، أريد أن أتحدث عن ماذا يعني أن تفهم شيئاً
and what we mean by understanding something.
وماذا نقصد بفهم الأشياء.
That's my aim here.
إنه هدفي هنا.
And my claim is that you understand something
وادعائي هنا هو أنك تفهم الشيء
if you have the ability to view it from different perspectives.
عندما تمتلك القدرة على عرضه من منظورات مختلفة.
Let's look at this letter. It's a beautiful R, right?
دعونا نلقي نظرة على هذا الحرف. إنه حرف الراء الجميل، صحيح؟
How do you know that?
كيف علمتم ذلك؟
Well, as a matter of fact, you've seen a bunch of R's,
حسناً، في الحقيقة، لقد رأيتم حزمة كم حروف الراء،
and you've generalized
ولقد عممتم
and abstracted all of these and found a pattern.
ولخصتم ذلك ووجدتم نمطاً.
So you know that this is an R.
لذا فقد علمتم أن ذلك حرف راء.
So what I'm aiming for here is saying something
لذا ما أهدف له هو أن أقول شيئاً
about how understanding and changing your perspective
حول كيف أن الفهم وتغيير منظورك
are linked.
مرتبطان.
And I'm a teacher and a lecturer,
وأنا مدرس ومحاضر،
and I can actually use this to teach something,
وأستطيع أن أستخدم هذا لتعليم شيء،
because when I give someone else another story, a metaphor, an analogy,
لأني عندما أعطي شخصًا آخرًا قصة مختلفة، استعارة، أو مشابهة،
if I tell a story from a different point of view,
إذا رويت قصة من وجهة نظر مختلفة،
I enable understanding.
فإني أمكِّنك من الفهم.
I make understanding possible,
أجعل الفهم ممكنًا،
because you have to generalize over everything you see and hear,
لأنك يجب أن تعمم فوق كل شيء تراه وتسمعه،
and if I give you another perspective, that will become easier for you.
وإذا أعطيتك منظورًا آخر فسيصبح أسهل لك.
Let's do a simple example again.
دعونا نقوم بمثال آخر مجدداً.
This is four and three. This is four triangles.
هذه هي أربعة وثلاثة. هذه هي أربعة مثلثات.
So this is also four-thirds, in a way.
لذا فهذه أيضاً أربعة أثلاث، بهذه الطريقة.
Let's just join them together.
دعونا نربطها معاً .
Now we're going to play a game; we're going to fold it up
الآن سوف نلعب معاً لعبة؛ سوف نقوم بطيِّها
into a three-dimensional structure.
في مجسم ثلاثي الأبعاد.
I love this.
أحب هذا.
And let's just take two of them and put them together.
ودعونا نأخذ اثنين منها ونضعها معاً.
So this is what is called an octahedron.
لذا هذا ما يسمى بثماني الأوجه.
It's one of the five platonic solids.
إنه واحد من المجسمات الأفلاطونية الخمسة.
Now we can quite literally change our perspective,
الآن نحن نستطيع حرفياً أن نغير منظورنا،
because we can rotate it around all of the axes
لأننا نستطيع أن نديره حول كل المحاور
and view it from different perspectives.
وأن نعرضه بمنظورات مختلفة.
And I can change the axis,
وأستطيع أن أغير المحاور،
and then I can view it from another point of view,
و أستطيع أن أعرضه من وجهة نظر مختلفة،
but it's the same thing, but it looks a little different.
لكنه نفس الشيء، ولكنه يبدو مختلفًا قليلًا.
I can do it even one more time.
وأستطيع أن أفعلها مرة أخرى أيضًا.
Every time I do this, something else appears,
في كل مرة أفعل ذلك، يظهر شيء آخر،
so I'm actually learning more about the object
لذا أنا فعلياً أتعلم أكثر حول الجسم
when I change my perspective.
عندما أغير منظوري.
I can use this as a tool for creating understanding.
يمكن أن أستخدم هذا لخلق الفهم.
I can take two of these and put them together like this
أستطيع أن آخذ اثنين منها وأضعها معاً هكذا
and see what happens.
وأرى ما الذي يحدث.
And it looks a little bit like the octahedron.
وهي تبدو أكثر مثل ثماني الأوجه.
Have a look at it if I spin it around like this.
ألقوا نظرة عليه إذا أدرناه هكذا.
What happens?
ما الذي يحدث؟
Well, if you take two of these, join them together and spin it around,
حسناً، إذا أخذت اثنين منها ووصلتها معاً وأدرتها،
there's your octahedron again,
إنه ثماني الأوجه مجدداً،
a beautiful structure.
مجسم رائع.
If you lay it out flat on the floor,
إذا وضعته بشكل مستوٍ على الأرض،
this is the octahedron.
هذا هو ثماني الأوجه.
This is the graph structure of an octahedron.
هذا هو مجسم ثماني الأوجه.
And I can continue doing this.
وأستطيع أن أستمر بفعل هذا.
You can draw three great circles around the octahedron,
يمكن أن أرسم ثلاث دوائر كبيرة حول ثماني الأوجه،
and you rotate around,
ويمكن أن تدور حوله،
so actually three great circles is related to the octahedron.
لذا هناك ثلاث دوائر عظيمة مرتبطة بثماني الأوجه.
And if I take a bicycle pump and just pump it up,
فإذا أخذنا مضخة دراجة ونفخناها،
you can see that this is also a little bit like the octahedron.
يمكنكم أن تروا أن هذا أيضاً يبدو كثماني أوجه.
Do you see what I'm doing here?
هل ترون ما الذي أفعله هنا؟
I am changing the perspective every time.
إني أغير منظوري كل مرة.
So let's now take a step back --
لذا دعونا نأخذ خطوة للخلف ...
and that's actually a metaphor, stepping back --
وهذه فعلياً استعارة، أخذ خطوة للخلف ...
and have a look at what we're doing.
ونلقي نظرة على ما نفعله.
I'm playing around with metaphors.
أنا فقط ألعب بالمتناظرات.
I'm playing around with perspectives and analogies.
أنا أعبث بالمنظورات والمتجانسات.
I'm telling one story in different ways.
وأروي قصة واحدة بطرق مختلفة.
I'm telling stories.
أنا أروي قصصًا.
I'm making a narrative; I'm making several narratives.
وأبتكر روايات؛ أبتكر العديد من الروايات.
And I think all of these things make understanding possible.
وأنا أعتقد أن كل هذه الأشياء تجعل الفهم ممكنًا.
I think this actually is the essence of understanding something.
أعتقد أن هذا هو جوهر فهم الأشياء.
I truly believe this.
أؤمن بذلك بصدق.
So this thing about changing your perspective --
لذا هذا الشيء حول تغيير منظورك...
it's absolutely fundamental for humans.
إنه أمر رئيسي للبشر.
Let's play around with the Earth.
دعونا نلعب بالكرة الأرضية.
Let's zoom into the ocean, have a look at the ocean.
دعونا نكبِّر الصورة إلى المحيط، ألقوا نظرة على المحيط.
We can do this with anything.
يمكننا فعل ذلك مع أي شيء.
We can take the ocean and view it up close.
يمكننا أن نأخذ المحيط ونعرضه بشكل قريب.
We can look at the waves.
يمكن أن ننظر إلى الأمواج.
We can go to the beach.
يمكن أن نذهب إلى الشاطئ.
We can view the ocean from another perspective.
يمكن أن نعرض المحيط من منظور مختلف.
Every time we do this, we learn a little bit more about the ocean.
في كل وقت نفعل ذلك، نتعلم شيئاً آخر حول المحيط.
If we go to the shore, we can kind of smell it, right?
إذا ذهبنا إلى الشاطئ، يمكننا أن نشم رائحة المحيط، صحيح؟
We can hear the sound of the waves.
يمكن أن نسمع أصوات الأمواج.
We can feel salt on our tongues.
يمكن أن نشعر بالملح على ألسنتنا.
So all of these are different perspectives.
لذا كل هذا حول منظور مختلف.
And this is the best one.
وهذا هو أفضلها.
We can go into the water.
يمكن أن نذهب داخل الماء.
We can see the water from the inside.
يمكن أن نرى الماء من الداخل.
And you know what?
وهل تعلمون ماذا؟
This is absolutely essential in mathematics and computer science.
هذا جوهري في الرياضيات وعلوم الحاسوب.
If you're able to view a structure from the inside,
إذا كنت قادرا على رؤية الجسم من الداخل،
then you really learn something about it.
فيمكن أن تتعلم شيئاً عنه.
That's somehow the essence of something.
وهذا بشكل ما جوهر الأشياء.
So when we do this, and we've taken this journey
لذا عندما نفعل هذا، ونبدأ هذه الرحلة
into the ocean,
داخل المحيط،
we use our imagination.
يمكن أن نستخدم مخيلتنا.
And I think this is one level deeper,
وأعتقد أن هذا مستوى أعمق،
and it's actually a requirement for changing your perspective.
وهو فعلياً من متطلبات تغيير منظورنا.
We can do a little game.
يمكننا القيام بلعبة صغيرة.
You can imagine that you're sitting there.
يمكن أن تتخيل أنك تجلس هناك.
You can imagine that you're up here, and that you're sitting here.
يمكن أن تتصور أنك هناك وأنت تجلس هنا.
You can view yourselves from the outside.
يمكن أن تعاين نفسك من الخارج.
That's really a strange thing.
إن هذا لشيء مختلف.
You're changing your perspective.
أنتم تغيرون منظوركم.
You're using your imagination,
أنتم تستخدمون مخيلتكم،
and you're viewing yourself from the outside.
وترون أنفسكم من الخارج.
That requires imagination.
إنه يتطلب مخيلة.
Mathematics and computer science are the most imaginative art forms ever.
الرياضيات وعلوم الحاسوب هي أقصى أشكال الفن التخيلي.
And this thing about changing perspectives
وهذا الشيء حول تغيير منظوركم
should sound a little bit familiar to you,
يجب أن يبدو مألوفًا لديكم،
because we do it every day.
لأننا نقوم بذلك كل يوم.
And then it's called empathy.
وهذا ما يدعى بالتعاطف.
When I view the world from your perspective,
عندما أرى العالم من منظوركم،
I have empathy with you.
فأنا أتعاطف معكم.
If I really, truly understand
إذا كنت أفهم حقًّا
what the world looks like from your perspective,
كيف يبدو العالم من وجهة نظركم،
I am empathetic.
فأنا متعاطف.
That requires imagination.
هذا يتطلب مخيلة.
And that is how we obtain understanding.
وهذه هي كيفية حصولنا على الفهم.
And this is all over mathematics and this is all over computer science,
وهذا كله موجود في الرياضيات وهذا كله موجود في علم الحاسوب
and there's a really deep connection between empathy and these sciences.
وهناك بحق اتصال عميق بين التعاطف وهذه العلوم.
So my conclusion is the following:
لذا فإن استنتاجي هو التالي:
understanding something really deeply
إن فهم شيء بشكل عميق جداً
has to do with the ability to change your perspective.
مرتبط بالقدرة على تغيير منظورك.
So my advice to you is: try to change your perspective.
فنصيحتي لكم هي: جرِّبوا أن تغيروا منظوركم.
You can study mathematics.
يمكن أن تدرسوا الرياضيات.
It's a wonderful way to train your brain.
إنها طريقة رائعة لتدريب أدمغتكم.
Changing your perspective makes your mind more flexible.
تغيير منظوركم يجعل أدمغتكم أكثر مرونة.
It makes you open to new things,
هذا يجعلكم منفتحين على أشياء جديدة،
and it makes you able to understand things.
وهذا يمكِّنكم من فهم الأشياء.
And to use yet another metaphor:
ولاستخدام استعارة أخرى:
have a mind like water.
امتلك عقلًا مثل الماء.
That's nice.
هذا لطيف.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)